Guide to the Subway Station Photographs Collection BCMS.0005
Brooklyn Collection
Subway Station Photographs Collection
1923-1950
Center for Brooklyn History
BCMS.0005
0.4 Linear Feet in 1 document box
Photographs of some of Brooklyn's elevated and subway trains, stations, and tracks.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Brian Merlis in 2009.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in three series by subject.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of 100 black and white 8 x 10 in. photographs depicting Brooklyn subway stations, cars, tracks and one photo reproduction of a subway map.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Related Materials
Digitized photographs of subway construction
Coppola, P. (1984). Silver Connections. Maplewood, NJ: Four Oceans Press.
Historical Note
The Interborough Rapid Transit Company (IRT) began construction of the first subway line in New York City in 1900. In 1909, construction began on Brooklyn's first subway line, the 4th Avenue subway. To encourage the rapid growth of subway construction, in 1913 the City of New York divided the disbursement of contracts between two companies: the IRT and the Brooklyn Rapid Transit Company (BRT), which was later renamed the Brooklyn-Manhattan Transit Corporation (BMT). Under the "dual contract" system, the IRT was awarded rights to expand the existing Manhattan, Brooklyn, and Bronx lines, while the BMT was awarded contracts for the construction of new lines in Manhattan, Brooklyn, and Queens. In the 1920s, the city-owned Independent Subway System (IND) was established to further expand the capacity of the city's subway system, as well as to compete with the privately-owned IRT and BMT. The IND's first completed line, the Eighth Avenue subway, opened in 1932.
In 1940, the IRT and BMT were acquired by the city and all three lines were consolidated with the IND into the New York City Board of Transportation. In 1953, the New York City Transit Authority (NYCTA) was established as a public benefit corporation to operate the subway system, and in 1968 the NYCTA was placed under the control of the Metropolitan Transit Authority, which continues to oversee and operate New York City's subway system.
Source: "History of Public Transportation in New York City," New York Transit Museum, accessed December 9, 2010, http://www.transitmuseumeducation.org/trc/background
Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Subway stations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Subways |z New York (State) |z Kings County
- Stations
  - 7th Avenue, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 9th Avenue, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 20th Avenue, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 34th Street, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 36th Street, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Flatbush Avenue, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Fort Hamilton, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Franklin Avenue, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Gates Avenue, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Greene Avenue, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Marcy Avenue, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Montrose Avenue, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Myrtle Avenue, 1930, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - New Lots Avenue, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Newkirk Avenue, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Nostrand Avenue, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Pacific Street, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Park Place, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Prospect Avenue, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Prospect Park, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Reid Avenue, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Rockaway Avenue, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Sands Street, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Sutter Avenue, 1932, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Tompkins Avenue, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Unidentified stations, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Cars & Map
  - Subway cars, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Subway map, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Tracks
  - Broadway Junction, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Church Avenue Line, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Lexington Avenue Line, from Dekalb Avenue, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Lexington Avenue Line, from Franklin Avenue, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Lexington Avenue Line, from Greene Avenue, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Lexington Avenue Line, from Myrtle Avenue, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Lexington Avenue Line, from Nostrand Avenue, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Lexington Avenue Line, from Reid Avenue, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Lexington Avenue Line, from Sumner Avenue, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Lexington Avenue Line, from Tompkins Avenue, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Manhattan Bridge, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Unidentified tracks, 1923-1947 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Myrtle Avenue Line, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Williamsburg Bridge, circa 1932 (Box 1, Folder 42)